Okay.
בוקר
טוב Boker tov again.
We are on page עמוד, amud, sorry, דף צ"ג. daf tsadik gimmel.
Nice to be here. I want to start back on צ"ב tsadik
beis in the middle of עמוד ב' amud beis of צ"ב, tsadik
beis, just a tiny bit
to explain something that I thought was very beautiful, and then we'll
skip and go back to the bottom of צ"ב ב' tsadik beis
beis to where you left off yesterday. So the line that I'm
looking to start in the middle of צ"ב ב' tsadik beis beis
starts with the word אבי אבא מהם. Avi Aba Mehem. It's
really in the middle.
Really in the middle.
Okay, and then the next thing asks ומאן נינהו מתים שהחיה יחזקאל?
Uman nin hu meisim shehechaya Yechezkel? Who are these dead that יחזקאל
Yechezkel revived in the valley? And there are five groups, and I
think that for, I would like to suggest, and you know, take
it or leave it, that for around 2,000 years those five groups
didn't make as much sense as maybe they make in the last
100 years, and that's why maybe there was a second look. Okay,
I can do, did you find them? Yeah. Okay. So the first
group is בני אפרים שמנו לקץ וטעו. Bnei Ephraim shemanu laketz veta'u.
So what do we mean by that, or I, what I'd like
to say what the גמרא Gemara means by that is we have
different calculations when the slavery is supposed to be over, right? The
slavery in Egypt is supposed to be over, we know it's 400
years, unclear when it exactly starts. We have a group that hastens
the גאולה, geulah, right? That pushes for faster redemption and rush
ahead, and they get attacked in the land, they come too soon,
הרגום אנשי גת הנולדים בארץ, Haragu amshei Gat hanoladim ba'aretz,
the people of גת Gat who were already in the land, the
land is not ready,
killed them. Okay, that's group one. These are the people that push
ahead. Opinion two, שמואל Shmuel says אלו בני אדם שכפרו בתחיית המתים.
Elu bnei adam shekafru bitchiyas hameisim. So these are people that reject
the notion of a future and the פסוק pasuk they quote, which
again in the last 100 years was borrowed into something that I
think everybody's familiar with, is יבשו עצמותינו ואבדה תקותנו. Yaveshu atzmoiseinu ve'avda
sikvaseinu. Of course what do we say, right, in the modern state
of Israel, לא אבדה תקותנו, lo avda tikvateinu, we have not lost
our hope. But the second group is people that lost all hope.
Maybe they assimilated. We did not
necessarily lose them physically, but these are people that lost hope of
our faith, and eventually when they died, they too are included in
יחזקאל's Yechezkel תחיית המתים. techiyas hameisim. Rabbi ירמיה, Yirmeya, which I really
like, he says אלו בני אדם שאין בהן לחלוחית של מצוה. Elu
bnei adam she'ein bahen lachluchis shel mitzvah. These are people that have
no moisture to their מצוה. mitzvah. So very beautiful, I think, he
doesn't say these are people that don't have מצוות. mitzvos. These are
people that do מצוות. mitzvos.
Or he could be saying the opposite, he's saying they're so, not
only do they not have any מצוות, mitzvos, but they even have
a residue of a מצוה. mitzvah. It could be just the exact
opposite potentially.
Maybe, maybe. I think he takes on,
on, it's like the moisture of the rain, it's not rain, it's
not rain just a little bit, they don't even have that.
That's
a bit of interpretation here. What is? If they're totally bereft of
even the slightest merit.
Okay,
so preparing for this, listening for different lectures, at least one of
the opinions is that the גמרא Gemara could have said אלו בני
אדם שאין בהן מצוות. Elu bnei adam she'ein bahen mitzvos.
It could have said these are people without מצוות. mitzvos. It takes
the phrase העצמות היבשות, ha'atzamos hayeveshos, the dry bones, like what are
we thinking that these are wet bones? Of course they're dry bones,
right? So adding the word dry just gives it another layer of
intensity to the dryness. So he suggests, I'll tell you about it
more later, that these are people that they call them the דתיים
יבשים, dati'im yeveshim, like people that they don't have the joy,
yes, the letter of but not the spirit, and thinking about it
further, you know, maybe you want to think about Rabbi עקיבא Akiva
and letting water change the rocks, right? How much do we let
מצוות mitzvos get to us or not, you know, or like we
do it on the outside but it doesn't affect us? So that's
also one group that we know nowadays and probably existed back then
included in the Jewish people and still revived by the חזון העצמות
היבשות, chazon ha'atzamos hayeveshos, by the dry bones.
The one before that they've like no hope as a Jewish people
so they are assimilated. They get lost to our to the people
who metaphorically.
Yeah. This is yeah.
That's why I went back. Okay. רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha
says אלו בני אדם שחיפו את ההיכל כולו שקצים ורמסים. Elu b'nei
adam shechipu et haheichal kulo shkatzim uremasim. This is a very provocative
kind of image. These are people that plaster or cover the sanctuary
with שקצים ורמסים shkatzim uremasim like with the most abhorrent right creatures.
What is it? So maybe also can be understood metaphorically as people
that completely reject the religious path and not only they don't do
it but they like smear it to cover it with disgusting things.
מומר להכעיס. Mumar Lehachis.
Yeah. Okay
and then the fifth category which is totally strange interesting you know
and maybe more to it than we than we read. It is
stated by רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So we know a lot of
things about רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan but one of the things we
know is about his appearance. What do we know about him?
He has he was he has very thick eyebrows. רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. No that's somebody else.
No he was he was he's very beautiful right?
He's very thick eyebrows and then you know silver tongs to like
you
know look at it and that's why.
Oh
that's when he's like very old right? In his encounter with רב
כהנא Rav Kahana right? And he says like pick up my eyelids.
I'm glad I know that one. Okay. But in his youth right?
There's stories about him that he sits at the entrance right? That
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish falls for him at the river that he
sits at the entrance to the מקוה Mikvah to inspire women because
he's so beautiful and this and that.
Interestingly we don't know about other beautiful people in our history or
I don't know following and yet he's talking here so like the
group that he's talking the fifth one are the בחורים שהיו מגנים
את החמה ביופיים. Bachurim shehayu meganim et hachama beyofyam. And so the
dead in בקעת דורא. Bik'at Dura. Yeah yeah yeah.
These are
the dead in בקעת דורא. Bik'at Dura. Keep going. אלו מתים שבבקעת
דורא. Elu metim shebeBik'at Dura. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan מנהר
אשל עד רבת בקעת דורא. Mina'har Eshel ad Rabbath Bik'at Dura. בקעת
דורא Bik'at Dura is in Syria. So this is on the possibly
route to the
גלות. Galut. בשעה שהגלה נבוכדנצר הרשע את ישראל Besha'ah shehiglah Nevuchadnezzar harasha
et Yisrael when נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar exiled Israel היו בהם בחורים שהיו מגנים
את החמה ביופיים. Hayu bahem bachurim shehayu meganim et hachama beyofyam. They
were so beautiful they like shaded the and
the plain is where נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar erected a golden colossus and he
wanted everybody bow down and you know חנניה מישאל ועזריה. Chananiah Mishael
v'Azariah. רגע. Rega.
חנניה. Chananiah. We're going to get to חנניה מישאל ועזריה Chananiah Mishael
v'Azariah in just a minute. But we now have these good I
don't want to get bogged on it but we now have these
good looking guys that overshadow the sun with their beauty right? And
the Chaldean women see them and become sexually aroused. They tell their
husband. The husband tell the king. The king command to kill them.
And still whether when they see them or you know they still
get excited about them the women. The king gives a command and
tramples them. And those that is the fifth group that gets woken
up
with the prophecy of the dry bones of Ezekiel. So
think a little bit about these two thousand years especially about the
Nazi era the hundred years maybe before that the caricatures of the
Jews. We did not walk around in the world thinking ourselves beautiful.
And yet in the last 80 70 100 years all of a
sudden there's a new image of a new Jew in Israel right?
And the posters now have the צבר Tzabar and he is whatever
has beautiful eyes and is sun-tanned and is hard-working and all of
a sudden there is a beauty queen I don't remember how many
years ago who is Jewish Israeli. Gal Gadot.
And there's Wonder Woman.
So Gal Gadot. Yeah Gal Gadot won a beauty contest in America.
Miss America. But in the end there was an Israeli too. So
like all of a sudden there's there's a change. So whether we
want to take this and you know take this whole vision of
the dry bones and look at what it looks like in the
last hundred years right? That whether these people are overly militant or
they're assimilated or they're just doing the religious thing by rote and
they don't really care or they kick off the whole religious thing
or they're like you
know whatever youthful and All of those are included. This is when
we talk about כל ישראל, Kol Yisrael, all of those are included.
Okay.
But the last one, בשעה שהפיל. besha'ah shehipil. Okay.
You were already there yesterday, but we will go back.
Hold on, hold on,
we've got this. Okay. This is beautiful and it's especially for David.
So, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, right? Right. תנו רבנן בשעה שהפיל נבוכדנצר
הרשע את חנניה מישאל ועזריה לכבשן האש אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא
ליחזקאל לך והחייה מתים בבקעת דורא.
Tanu
Rabbanan
besha'ah shehipil Nevuchadnezzar harasha et Chananyah Mishael va'Azaryah lekivshan ha'esh amar lo
HaKadosh Baruch Hu leYechezkel lech vehachayeih metim beVik'at Dura.
At the same exact time, right, at the same בשעה, besha'ah, at
the time, in the hour, when נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar threw חנניה מישאל ועזריה
Chananyah Mishael va'Azaryah to the furnace. Talk about the furnace in just
a minute.
The Holy One Blessed Be He says to יחזקאל, Yechezkel, go revive
the dead in בקעת דורא. Bik'at Dura. So think
again, think about this in the context of Jewish history and these
are again also things that are worth a much longer conversation, but
חנניה מישאל ועזריה Chananyah Mishael va'Azaryah are being thrown in the furnace
because they refused to bow down. Why don't we know about 200,000
other people that are going to be thrown into the furnace because
they didn't bow down?
חנניה מישאל ועזריה Chananyah Mishael va'Azaryah were saved.
Maybe. Option one is they're the only ones that were saved, right?
Option two is that everybody else did bow down, right? We don't
even know anyone that was taken to be thrown into the furnace.
It doesn't tell us 200 went to the furnace, only these three
came out, right? These are the ones that נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar takes to
the furnace because everybody else bowed down to the whatever it was
60 אמות amot high or some statue that נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar put up.
So these are now the three last three people left to not
obey נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnezzar. He's going to annihilate them and with them the
whole problem of the Jewish people will be gone. What happened exactly
in the same time? בשעה, besha'ah,
that is the time that God says to יחזקאל, Yechezkel, go revive
the dead.
There's an aspect of it that we can just be like, yeah,
okay, the גמרא Gemara is just crazy, or there's an aspect of
it reading it in, you know, in this century as opposed to
in 1500 that is a little bit chilling, a little bit eerie.
And we talked about...
I think that might be the story of Jewish history.
Maybe. Yes, yes.
But it's like one fades and another one
rises.
That it does not, that it like rises from the ashes and
we'll see it a little bit that it starts, it starts again.
These are like the dead and a minute ago we saw that
they were crushed and gone, and yet
now
they're being revived and דווקא davka these מתים בבקעת דורא metim beVik'at
Dura that are like the beautiful, you know, guys that restart the
nation again.
I find it powerful
if coincidental then you can ignore it. I want to skip this
a little bit because we actually read through it and go to
the six lines from the bottom that starts with דוד בספר תהלים.
David beSefer Tehillim. The discussion I just skipped is the...
We didn't do תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan right after... I think the
six miracles occurred on that day.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's where I'm going. Oh, okay. Yes,
I said there's a tiny section that I skipped that the Rabbis
argue with the fact that נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar wants to praise השם Hashem
and almost be in competition with King דוד. David. And what's going
on there? But for starting a little late and being behind I
don't want to get bogged there. So let's go to תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. Okay? ששה נסים נעשו באותו היום. shisha nissim na'asu be'oto
hayom.
Not only were the dead revived by יחזקאל Yechezkel with the חזון
העצמות, Chazon HaAtzamot,
not
only חנניה מישאל ועזריה, Chananyah Mishael va'Azaryah, what exactly is the miracle
like we're going to unpack that miracle a little bit what happened
to them? So ששה נסים נעשו באותו היום, shisha nissim na'asu be'oto
hayom, six miracles ואלו הן: ve'elu hen: צף הכבשן ונפרץ הכבשן והומק
סודו ונהפך צלם על פניו ונשרפו ארבע מלכויות והחיה יחזקאל את המתים
בבקעת דורא. tzaf hakivshan venifratz hakivshan vehumak sodo venehepach tzelem al panav
venisrefu arba malchuyot vehichyah Yechezkel et hametim beVik'at Dura.
So not only the dead in בקעת דורא, Bik'at Dura, but all
these things. What is the כבשן? kivshan? What is that furnace that
מישאל, Mishael, חנניה, Chananya, מישאל, Mishael, and עזריה Azarya being thrown into?
The furnace, the כבשן kivshan is like a hot stove that's buried
in the ground. Okay, so that's an important piece of it, it's
fire that's buried in the ground. So if you throw anything in
it, you can't see what's going on inside. So if let's חס
וחלילה, chas v'chalila, if something someone gets thrown in it and comes
out alive on the other side, we will miss part of the
miracle. In order to see the fullness of the miracle, the first
thing that has to happen is the furnace rises up from where
it is in a sunken ground. Then it is breached, it is
cracked. Now we have a problem with הומק סודו. humak sodo. What
exactly does it mean? The
let's say conventional is that the כבשן, kivshan, the furnace, is made
out of limestone, it's made out of סיד. sid. And that סיד
sid opens up or dissipates.
Okay? Yes.
I mean, I would think, you know, like the base of it
sort of like melting, right? This is יסוד. yesod.
Okay, so is it יסוד, yesod, right? Is it סיד? sid? Is
it סוד, sod, like how it is constructed is now comes apart
and they walk out.
רש"י Rashi is סוד sud or...
סוד. sud. No, no, no, רש"י Rashi and somewhere... maybe it's a
typo.
I don't know, hang on.
Oh yeah, he says ושנשתנה הומק סודו כמו יסודו. v'shenishtana humak sodo
k'mo yesodo. משתופף. mishtofef. Okay. Right,
יסודו. yesodo.
Or then he says another one,
הומק סידו.
humak sido. Right, הסיד הכבשן נמס. hasid hakivshan namas. Right, מרוב חמימות.
merov
chamimut.
כך שמעתי והיה נמשכת לרחוק מההבל של אותו הסיד נשרפו אותן שישבו.
kach shamati v'haya nimshechet lirachok mehahavel shel oto hasid nisrefu otan sheyashvu.
Okay. So then we'll see in a minute that others were burned
while חנניה, מישאל, ועזריה Chananya Mishael vaAzarya went out. Okay. The next
thing is that the image, the graven image that נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar put
up was destroyed, it fell on its face, and four monarchies
or kings, we'll see in a minute, were burned instead.
And יחזקאל Yechezkel also revived the dead in בקעת דורא. Bik'at Dura.
בקעת... Bik'at... woah, sorry, בקעת דורא. Bik'at Dura. I feel like I'm
rushing. וכולהו גמרא וארבע מלכויות קרא. v'chulhu gemara v'arba malchuyot kra. So
all these things we know from מסורה, mesora, we know from right,
tradition. But one of them is קרא, kra, one of them is
a פסוק... pasuk...
as יחזקאל Yechezkel was a פסוק pasuk as it is written.
Don't know why they're saying it then this way.
Do you have something?
Just
asking the question.
Unless they're saying the timing of it is a גמרא, gemara, I
don't know.
Maybe. The fact that it all happened on the same day? Maybe.
But clearly it says וכולהו גמרא וארבע מלכויות קרא דכתיב. v'chulhu gemara
v'arba malchuyot kra dichtiv. Okay, and now we have a long Aramaic
thing. ונבוכדנצר מלכא שלח למכנש לאחשדרפניא סגניא פחוותא אדרגזריא גדבריא דתבריא תפתיא
וכל שלטוני מדינתא. v'Nevuchadnezzar malka shelach lemicnash la'achashdarpanaya siganaya pachvata adargazraya gadavraya
detavraya tifitaya v'chol shiltonei medinata.
Okay.
So now נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar sends... there should be seven here.
That he sends all the governors of his kingdom and calls them...
calls them up.
Okay.
This is in דניאל. Daniel. And it says, continuing, there were איתי
גוברין יהודאין, itai guvrin Yehuda'in, right? There's certain Jews that don't serve
your god and don't worship the golden image that you erected. As
it is written in the verse after the story of חנניה, מישאל,
ועזריה, Chananya Mishael vaAzarya
hold on a second, מתכנשין אחשדרפניא, mitkanshin achashdarpanaya, we have it also
in אסתר, Esther, סגניא
ופחוותא והדברי מלכא חזיין לגבריא אלך, siganaya ufachvata v'hadavrei malka chazayin legavraya
elech, etcetera. Okay.
As it is written, and the different kind of governors,
right, the king's counselors, gathered and saw these men. They saw חנניה,
מישאל, ועזריה Chananya Mishael vaAzarya, who emerged from the fire without harm.
Maybe eight ranks? He sends eight ranks of officials and only four
witnessed חנניה, מישאל, ועזריה Chananya Mishael v'Azarya emerge from the fire. So
there is a tradition or an understanding that four of them were
themselves burned in the fire. Maybe that's maybe part of this melting
and
the fire expanding.
Okay. Rashi says that. This is what he says: שלאציד
נשרפו אותן שהשליכו חנניה מישאל ועזריה לתוך כבשן האש. she'letzid nisrefo otan
she'hishlichu Hananya Mishael ve'Azarya l'toch kivshan ha'esh. According to Rashi, דיבור
המתחיל הוא הומק סודו,
dibbur hamatchil hu humak
sodo, at the end of it he says: נשרפו אותן שהשליכו מישאל
ועזריה חנניה מישאל לתוך כבשן האש. nisrefo otan she'hishlichu Mishael ve'Azarya Hananya
Mishael l'toch kivshan ha'esh. Okay. Moving on. תני דבי רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב
אפילו בשעת הסכנה לא ישנה אדם את עצמו מן הרבנות.
Tnai devei Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov: Afilu b'sha'at hasakanah lo yeshaneh adam
et atzmo min
harabbanut.
So this is interesting and הפוך afuch from another statement we have
in פרקי אבות. Pirkei Avot. Just give it one more second and
we will explain.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, it's not these exact wordings but there seems to be
this parallel to the story of Esther when
המן Haman says these people don't do this.
Right, right, no, don't do this. Yes.
Our more in-depth learning of this has a lot of aspects of
how we are in גלות. galut. And some of it we can
see, what kind of things we have to put up with, the
temperament of the rulers around,
overt and covert anti-Semitism,
how we respond,
as much as we can touch it, then we'll do, and if
not, next time. Okay. So now it says נאמר, ne'emar, right? We
have a פסוק pasuk also from Daniel that says באדין גבריא אלך
כפתו בסרבליהון פטישיהון וכרבלתהון
be'edin gavraya ilech
kaftu besarbalehon patishehon vecharbelatehon etc., etc. So the פסוק pasuk tells us
that these men, these three men, they were bound in their tunics,
cloaks, hats, they were fully clothed in their royal garments when they
were thrown into the fire. And for that,
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says אפילו בשעת הסכנה לא ישנה אדם את
עצמו מן הרבנות. afilu b'sha'at hasakanah lo yeshaneh adam et atzmo min
harabbanut. And
we have a problem, if you remember in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot,
we have a saying that says שנא את הרבנות, snai et harabbanut,
right? Reject the רבנות. rabbanut. That's a problem how we translate רבנות
rabbanut as being in power or statehood, kind of a place of
prominence, and don't get too close with the authorities. But here, yes.
So when I read it, an image that came to mind, there
is a movie that's called Friendship in Vienna about two girls that
are friends in Vienna in 1938. One
is 10, 12, and one set of parents joined the Nazi party
and one set of parents are Jewish.
Never mind the whole story, but 1938 the Nazis come to Vienna
and they take the Jews out of their homes to scrub the
streets with toothbrushes. And the grandfather says to the girl, help me
pick up my most beautiful tie, I want to look especially good
today.
And there is that part of don't get involved with the רבנות,
rabbanut, but if you're already in it, kind of maintain your dignity
and how we do it, how they did it, even though they
were thrown in the fire, they maintained their garments. All right, we
will move into צדיק ג׳. tzadik gimmel. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar
Rabbi Yochanan:
גדולים צדיקים יותר ממלאכי השרת, Gdolim tzadikim yoter mimalachei hasharet, as it
is said. So the צדיקים tzadikim are greater from מלאכי השרת. malachei
hasharet. Some of it
פשיטא. pishita. מלאכים malachim only have one job and the צדיקים tzadikim
can do more. Another interesting conversation is how do we
layer the different people? We also say במקום שבעלי תשובה עומדים צדיקים
לא עומדים. bemakom sheba'alei teshuvah omdim tzadikim lo omdim. It's how do
we create a hierarchy between all these layers? But here it's told
the צדיקים tzadikim are greater than מלאכי השרת, malachei hasharet, as it
is said in Daniel:
ענה ואמר הא אנא חזי גברין ארבעה שריין מהלכין בגוא נורא. Anah
ve'amar ha ana chazei gavrin arba sharin mehalechin bego nura. I see
four walking in the midst of the fire. וחבל לא איתי בהון,
Vechaval lo itai behon, no harm came to them.
ורביעיא דמי לבר אלהין. Verevi'aya domeh l'varya damei l'var elohin. And I
see a fourth one looking like בר אלהין, bar elohin, like the
son of God, i.e., like an angel. Except what happens? Three
come out.
Three come out.
So we lost one. So if this fourth one looked like a
son of God,
he didn't make it
out.
Maybe you
could say he stepped in to save them. Maybe he was an
angel, but I don't know.
Okay,
אמר רב תנחום בר חנילאי: Amar Rav Tanchum bar Chanilai: בשעה שיצאו
חנניה מישאל ועזריה מכבשן האש, besha'ah she'yatzu Chananyah Mishael va'Azaryah mi'kivshan ha'esh,
באו כל אומות העולם ותפחו לשונאיהן של ישראל על פניהם. ba'u kol
umot ha'olam ve'taphchu l'soneihen shel Yisrael al pneihem. Right? In at the
moment, at the time that Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah came out of
the furnace of fire, all the nations of the world
slapped the haters of Israel. This is a what's called סגי נהור,
sagi nahor, euphemism. It's meant to Israel, and slapped them and said
to them, אמרו להם: amru lahem: יש לכם אלוה כזה ואתם משתחווים
לצלם? yesh lachem eloh kaze ve'atem mishtachavim la'tzelem? You have such a
God that saves people out of the fire and is capable of
doing these kind of things and you bow down to a graven
image? מיד פתחו ואמר, mi'yad patchu ve'amru, they immediately opened and said,
from Daniel: לך השם הצדקה ולנו בושת הפנים כיום הזה. Lecha Hashem
ha'tzedakah u'lanu boshet ha'panim k'hayom ha'zeh. You השם, Hashem, you have righteousness,
צדקה, tzedakah, and we have בושת הפנים. boshet ha'panim. I'll show you
something nice in this a second.
But think about this that a פסוק pasuk that we're saying every
every benching time on Shabbat and we don't think about it, and
now I'll share it with you and now you won't be able
to not think about it. Right? What do we say in שיר
המעלות? Shir HaMa'alot?
אז יאמרו בגוים: az yomru va'goyim:
הגדיל השם לעשות עם אלה. higdil Hashem la'asot im eleh. And the
next פסוק pasuk
is: הגדיל השם לעשות עמנו.
higdil Hashem la'asot imanu. So רגע, rega, it should be opposite, right?
We should say look השם Hashem so great, and then the nations
of the world will be like, yeah, they got it pretty good.
But this is בשוב השם את שיבת ציון, beshuv Hashem et shivat
Tzion, right? When we sit in the גלות, Galut, we start buying,
this is what I said before, we start buying into what people
around us think. Sometimes they don't think nice things and we start
like getting more hunched. When the גוים Goyim says, look, הגדיל השם
לעשות עם אלה, higdil Hashem la'asot im eleh, then the next פסוק
pasuk we all of a sudden say, ah yeah, הגדיל השם לעשות
עמנו. higdil Hashem la'asot imanu. But we sometimes miss it. About בושת
הפנים, boshet ha'panim, I saw something nice over this Shabbat because it's
פרשת... parshat... פרשת parshat something, right? בראשית Bereishit
and whatever, one of the
sages... there's a lot of ways to unscramble the letters, right? אתב"ש,
Atbash, one of the...
יראי בושת yirei boshet goes with this בושת הפנים boshet ha'panim that
and as we start reading there should be some humility about us,
some humbleness.
It's something dangerous for today like in '67, the glory of the
Jews around the world and now we're getting the other side of
how we stand strong with our own...
But we start seeing ourselves in the eyes of how people are
seeing us. Yeah, yeah, of course, like
we're not empty like some things reflect on us and we reflect
on it.
It's also Esther again, the story of Esther. And then all the
other people want to convert to Judaism.
So
I listened to that too, or this came up in one of
the other lectures I was listening to. Is it a question if
מתיהדים mityahadim in מגילת אסתר Megillat Esther means that they wanted to
convert or that they became more favorable? What exactly is this structure
of the verb? It's a little bit of a strange verb. Backward.
We'll at least get to the top of צדיקים ב tzaddikim bet
or this will be the last time Rabbi Winzel lets me be.
Wind down.
All right.
אמר רב
שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן: Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar
Rabbi Yonatan: מאי דכתיב, mai de'chtiv, what is it that it says
in שיר השירים Shir HaShirim in the Song of Songs: אמרתי אעלה
בתמר אוחזה בסנסיניו. amarti e'eleh ve'tamar ochazah ve'sansinav. I will go up
in the palm date tree, right? And I will hold on to
its branches. Who says it? הקדוש ברוך הוא. Hakadosh Baruch Hu. אמרתי
אעלה בתמר אלו ישראל. Amarti e'eleh ve'tamar elu Yisrael. I will
go up with the palm tree and we can think about also
we know צדיק כתמר יפרח, tzaddik katamar yifrach, right? And there is
a metaphor of the Jewish people being like a תמר, tamar, that
think about the לולב, lulav, right? The לולב lulav is the לב,
lev, the heart of the תמר. tamar. The תמר tamar tree has
one heart, we're supposed to be a people of one heart, you
know, one focus around around השם. Hashem. ועכשיו לא עלה בידי, Ve'achshav
lo alah b'yadi, which I really like this part of me that...
of the God of the, you know, the God of the rabbis.
That like He's God. He can do anything. He can get these
people out of the fire. But it's really hard to raise the
Jewish people to do the right thing. So He tried, but לא
עלה בידי lo ala beyadi wasn't quite successful, אלא סנסן אחד של
חנניה מישאל ועזריה. ela sansan echad shel Chananya Mishael vaAzarya.
There is also a commentary, just to put on the radar,
that תמר tamar could mean תמר tamar the wife of יהודה Yehuda
who there's also a tradition that she was willing to be thrown
into the furnace of fire or you know in order to save
the Jewish people. So what do we do with יהודה? Yehuda? יהודים?
Yehudim? The תמר? tamar? And kind of a קל וחומר kal vachomer
of course, if she was willing to do this for a human
being, for השם Hashem even more so. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, מאי דכתיב, mai dichtiv, let's look at a different פסוק
pasuk
in זכריה: Zecharia: ראיתי הלילה והנה איש רוכב על סוס אדום והוא
עומד בין ההדסים אשר במצולה. Raiti halaila vehineh ish rocheiv al sus
adom vehu omed bein hahadasim asher bametzula. This is by the way
where אסתר Esther comes back because of the הדסים hadasim and the
fact that the righteous are called הדסים hadasim and that אסתר's Esther
other name is הדסה, Hadassah, right?
Wait, is this just like the גמרא Gemara just free thinking?
I don't know where all this came from. I think some of
the free thinking, well, one we're going to come back to חנניה
מישאל ועזריה Chananyah Mishael veAzaryah in a little bit of this, well,
here we have them right away, right? The סנסן אחד ושל חנניה
מישאל ועזריה. sansan echad veshel Chananya Mishael vaAzarya.
And previously also. And back to the beginning of this whole פרק
perek of כל ישראל יש להם חלק. kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek.
Who is this כל ישראל kol Yisrael that we're looking at? But
a lot around חנניה מישאל ועזריה Chananyah Mishael veAzaryah and דניאל Daniel
will come in just a minute. Stay tuned. Okay, what do we
mean, what do we mean by this פסוק? pasuk? What is the
לילה, laila, right? ראיתי הלילה. Raiti halaila. ביקש הקדוש ברוך הוא להפוך
את כל העולם כולו ללילה. Bikesh Hakadosh Baruch Hu lehafoch et kol
ha'olam kulo le'laila. Like the Holy One Blessed Be He wants to
turn the whole world to night because basically everybody left the faith,
everybody left the way. Only those three are left. והנה איש רוכב.
Vehineh ish rocheiv. So it says and behold there's an איש. ish.
איש ish is a very
loaded word in our scripture, from משה Moshe when משה Moshe looks
around ואין איש ve'ein ish and when it says במקום שאין אנשים
הייה אתה איש. bemakom she'ein anashim heye ata ish. Sometimes איש ish
is אליהו. Eliyahu. What is this איש? ish? Here they say איש
ish is הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu because it says
in שירת הים, Shirat Hayam, השם איש מלחמה השם שמו. Hashem ish
milchama Hashem shemo. So that's His name, right? He is the איש.
ish. על סוס אדום. Al sus adom. ביקש הקדוש ברוך הוא להפוך
את העולם כולו לדם. Bikesh Hakadosh Baruch Hu lehafoch et ha'olam kulo
ledam.
Yes, metaphors of what is red, what is night,
what happens in this turmoil when almost all the Jewish people and
with them their faith is being destroyed. כיוון שנסתכל בחנניה מישאל ועזריה
נתקררה דעתו. Keivan shenistakel beChananya Mishael vaAzarya nitkarera da'ato. He chilled a
little bit. We have a passionate God. And it says והוא עומד
בין ההדסים אשר במצולה, vehu omed bein hahadasim asher bametzula,
right? Go back, it says He's standing among the, now what do
we do with the הדסים? hadasim? Is God really in the woods?
And so like He's feeling a little better because He likes being
in the הדסים hadasim forest? Or as the גמרא Gemara suggests, ואין
הדסים אלא צדיקים. ve'ein hadasim ela tzaddikim. And here comes אסתר Esther
שנאמר ויהי אומן את הדסה, shenemar vayehi omen et Hadassah, right? She
did not...
she had two names. What is the usefulness of her name הדסה?
Hadassah? And one of the commentaries I was listening, there is attention
to the fact that a הדס hadas has three leaves. And what
does it mean? Is it that תורה עבודה גמילות חסדים? Torah Avodah
Gemilut Chasadim?
Okay, חנניה מישאל ועזריה, Chananyah Mishael veAzaryah, תורה, Torah,
צדקה, tzedaka, תורה עבודה גמילות חסדים, Torah Avodah Gemilut Chasadim, like whatever.
Three, אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak vaYaakov, like there's different groups of
three. Somehow the הדסים hadasim come to symbolize the צדיקים. tzaddikim.
Are we just building up on לולב lulav also? The different component
parts.
You think because the תמר tamar and now the הדסים. hadasim.
I will not... I often find that they have so many
wires and layers, you know, when they talk about things. I mean,
the ערבה arava is like obvious to me, right? We talk about
ערבות, aravot, right? In בבל Bavel we sit on ערבות aravot always,
no? שם תלינו כינורותינו,
Sham
talinu
kinoroteinu, like we sit on the willows in בבל. Bavel. Why you
look at me like this? Yeah. We don't even have an ערבה...
arava... Bavel בבל Bavel now is tzulah צולה tzulah metzulah
מצולה, metzulah,
right? In charvi חרבי, charvi, it’s dried. Ve’naharotayikh hovish ונהרותייך הוביש, ve’naharotayikh
hovish,
hovish הוביש, hovish, look at like I can’t
so dry out.
I can’t but fall in love with the Hebrew. Right, but also
lehitbayes להתבייש, lehitbayes, you’ll be ashamed with with what you’re doing, right?
Miyad milifnei rogez naasim srukim veadumim naasu levanim מיד מלפני רוגז נעשים
סרוקים ואדומים נעשו לבנים. miyad milifnei rogez naasim srukim veadumim naasu levanim.
This is like metaphors for Hashem resting from his anger.
How did he get Bavel out of that?
He said, ein metzulah ela Bavel אין מצולה אלא בבל. ein metzulah
ela Bavel. Yeah. Oh, how did he get? Because the pasuk פסוק
pasuk in Yeshayahu ישעיהו Yeshayahu omer lemetzulah charvi venaharotayikh hovish אומר למצולה
חרבי ונהרותייך הוביש. omer lemetzulah charvi venaharotayikh hovish. Bavel בבל Bavel is
a place of the naharot נהרות naharot and the place where everything
happens. Amar Rav Papa אמר רב פפא amar Rav Papa shema mina
sus yachivra malei lealma שמע מינה סוס חיורא מעלי לעלמא. shema mina
sus yachivra malei lealma. A white horse is a good sign. If
you dream of a white horse, good sign. Let’s go for that.
Okay.
Gives gives peace. Okay. Verabanan ורבנן, verabanan, rega rega rega
רגע רגע רגע, rega rega רגא, verabanan leichan azlu ורבנן להיכן אזלו?
verabanan leichan azlu? Now wait a second, we had this whole conversation.
Chananya, Mishael, and Azarya חנניה משאל ועזריה, Chananya Mishael veAzarya, they walked
out of the furnace. And where did they go? We have different
opinions. I will erase. Okay. Amar Rav אמר רב, amar Rav, one
opinion, be'ayin hara metu בעין הרע מתו. be'ayin hara metu. After all
this, davka דווקא davka because of all this, there is an opinion
in Bava Metzia בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, don’t like don’t take me
there, that ninety-nine percent of the world die me’ayin hara מעין הרע,
me’ayin hara, that like this is the kin'ah קנאה kin'ah is so
strong, what does it say about us humans? Like how do we
look at each other? Okay. One opinion. Shmuel amar berok tav’u שמואל
אמר ברוק טבעו. Shmuel amar berok tav’u. Berok ברוק berok is like
spit but like in despising, right? That they were like we don't
care about you.
Rashi רש"י Rashi says...
Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, not going... Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan right says, alu le'Eretz Yisrael venasu nashim ve'holidu banim uvanot
עלו לארץ
ישראל ונשאו נשים והולידו בנים ובנות
alu le'Eretz Yisrael
venasu
nashim ve'holidu banim uvanot which is like the atzamot yeveshot עצמות יבשות.
atzamot yeveshot.
Yes, right? The revival. Now they say, hey, this is not new
opinions. Kitnai
כתנאי. kitnai. This already we've seen this in earlier generation. Rabbi Eliezer
omer be’ayin hara metu רבי אליעזר אומר בעין הרע מתו. Rabbi Eliezer
omer be’ayin hara metu. Rabbi Yehoshua omer berok tav’u רבי יהושע אומר
ברוק טבעו. Rabbi Yehoshua omer berok tav’u. Vechachamim omrim וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim
omrim, Rabbi Yochanan and the chachamim, alu le'Eretz Yisrael venasu nashim ve'holidu
banim uvanot עלו לארץ ישראל ונשאו נשים והולידו בנים ובנות alu le'Eretz
Yisrael venasu nashim ve'holidu banim uvanot shene’emar שנאמר, shene’emar, we have a
pasuk פסוק pasuk with it. Shema na Yehoshua Kohen Gadol ata vere'echa
hayoshevim lefanecha ki anshei mofet hema שמע נא יהושע כהן גדול אתה
ורעיך היושבים לפניך כי אנשי מופת המה. Shema na Yehoshua Kohen Gadol
ata vere'echa hayoshevim lefanecha ki anshei mofet hema. It's talked about Yehoshua
the high priest when when he's approached as you and your friends
that are sitting with you because they are people of a miracle.
Who can be the people of the miracle, right? Eizehem anashim shenasa
lahem mofet? Hevei omer zeh Chananya Mishael veAzarya איזהו הם אנשים שנעשה
להם מופת הוי אומר זה חנניה משאל ועזריה.
eizehem anashim shenasa lahem
mofet hevei omer zeh Chananya Mishael veAzarya. VeDaniel ודניאל? veDaniel? Right? Where
is Daniel? What, is it possible that Daniel bowed down to the
graven image and only those three were left not bowing down? So
Daniel leichan azal דניאל להיכן אזל? Daniel leichan azal? Now we also
have three opinions, each one with its beautiful implications and metaphors. Amar
Rav lemichra nahara raba biTverya אמר רב למכרא נהרא רבא בטבריא. amar
Rav lemichra nahara raba biTverya. He went to dig up the Movila
Artzi מוביל הארצי, Movila Artzi, the national water aqueduct in Israel in
Tverya טבריא. Tverya.
Table, long... of course, like this is the tradition to dig up
in Tverya טבריא. Tverya. No, two things on this pasuk פסוק pasuk
to think about. What is Tverya? Like Tverya טבריא Tverya is the
center of Israel. There's one opinion that it's called Tverya טבריא Tverya
because of Tiberius, right? Because of the ruler. But in Hebrew, tabur
טבור tabur is the belly button, right? So it's like Tverya טבריא
Tverya is like the the belly button of Israel, like the the
center of Israel and he goes to dig up water to bring
Torah, right? To revive a center in Tverya טבריא Tverya which we
know later existed. Okay. UShmuel amar leatoyei bizra deaspasta ושמואל אמר לאתויי
ביזרא דאספסתא. ushmuel amar leatoyei bizra deaspasta. And one of the explanations
is, Shmuel, you probably know it better, is the like the chief
dayan דיין dayan in dinei mamonot דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, right? He's
like the economist. So he looks at what economical ventures can be
done here. So he says, oh, he brings
seeds or right special kind of choice of alfalfa seeds to to
that was not yet there. So he takes care of the economy.
VeRabbi Yochanan
ורבי יוחנן veRabbi Yochanan says, what look some of us slightly familiar.
He went, okay, amar leatoyei chazirei deAlexandria shel Mitzrayim אמר לאתויי חזירי
דאלכסנדריא של מצרים. amar leatoyei chazirei deAlexandria shel Mitzrayim. He went to
get pigs from Alexandria from from Egypt. Right. Ini איני? ini? Like
this is like strange, the Gemara גמרא... Gemara... Yeah, as opposed to
anything else, but דווקא davka pigs, דווקא davka from Egypt, what's going
on with the pigs there?
והתניא V'ha tanya תודוס הרופא Thodos HaRofe אמר: amar: אין פרה וחזירה
יוצא מאלכסנדריא של מצרים שאין חותכין האם שלה. ein para v'chazira yotzei
m'Alexandria shel Mitzrayim she'ein chotchin ha'em shela. This, the Egyptians
have a special breed of pigs and cows and they don't let
any breeding pigs and cows out of Egypt unless they cut their
womb out so that they have the unique breed and no one
else can compete with them. The babies that they don't need, they
eat, so they don't yet cut their womb. Suppose, here, and it
continues and said, okay, בשביל שלא תלד, bishvil shelo teled, זוטרי אייתי
בלא דעתא דאתו. zutari aytei belo da'ata d'atu. So Rabbi Yochanan when
he went there, he took the little ones because otherwise a whole
problem would what exactly like this now animal is wounded, right, this
and this. This is what the rabbis say where Daniel went.
No, but was he sent
by Nebuchadnezzar or he was on his own? So he's like an
advisor of the king, right, he's his...
right, right, right. They don't eat meat in Egypt.
I don't
know what you're thinking
that he ate the pigs. What? I think that it says he's
a doctor and maybe there was
some medicinal... תודוס Thodos the doctor,
somebody says, right?
Yes, but no one goes out of Alexandria...
well, yes,
but this is because the pigs like... okay.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: שלושה היו באותה עצה shlosha hayu b'ota eitza
הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu ודניאל v'Daniel
ונבוכדנצר. v'Nevuchadnezzar. So there were three sitting in this, in
this plan, that Daniel should not be in בבל Bavel when חנניה
Chananya, מישאל Mishael, ועזריה v'Azarya are being thrown into the furnace because,
like, we'll see in a minute. Why? Why do we not want
him to be in בבל? Bavel? הקדוש ברוך הוא אמר: HaKadosh Baruch
Hu amar: יזל דניאל מהכא דלא לימרו בזכותו אינצל. yeizal Daniel mehacha
d'lo limru bizchuto inatzel.
So Daniel says God says, let Daniel not be here so that
people don't say that the three of them were saved, right, from
the furnace because of Daniel. It should
reflect their own righteousness. ודניאל אמר: v'Daniel amar: איזל מהכא דלא ליקיים
בי
פסילי
אלהיהם תשרפון באש.
eizal mehacha d'lo lekayem bi pesilei
eloheihem tisrefun ba'esh.
Daniel said: I better leave from here, right, because we'll see in
just a second, in a couple lines down, that Nebuchadnezzar like held
Daniel very high that he, you know, he would like, he fell
on his face as if he worshiped Daniel. So now if he
throws Daniel into the fire, Daniel becomes like one of their gods,
right, because Nebuchadnezzar bows down to him, and it says in דברים:
Devarim: פסילי אלהיהם תשרפון באש pesilei eloheihem tisrefun ba'esh you will burn
their idols in the fire. He does not want to be one
of their idols that will be burned in the fire. ונבוכדנצר אמר:
v'Nevuchadnezzar amar: יזיל דניאל מהכא דלא לימרו קלי לה לאלוהיה בנורא. yeizil
Daniel mehacha d'lo limru kali leh l'elohei beneura.
Daniel should go away from here so people don't say that Nebuchadnezzar
burned his own god in the fire. How do we, where do
we get this idea from? מנא לן דסגיד ליה? mna lan d'sagid
leh? Where do we get that he worshiped he, Nebuchadnezzar, worshiped him,
Daniel? It is said: באדין מלכא נבוכדנצר נפל על אנפוהי ולדניאל סגיד.
be'edayin malka Nevuchadnezzar nefal al anpohi u'l'Daniel sagid.
So there is a פסוק pasuk in דניאל Daniel that says that
the king Nebuchadnezzar fell on his face and
worshiped
Daniel. Since we're already talking about people in the fire, we have
a couple of other people that we have fire stories in the
context of גלות בבל Galut Bavel of that era, and so we're
going to talk about them now. So we have a פסוק pasuk
from ירמיהו: Yirmiyahu: כה אמר ה' צבאות אלוקי ישראל אל אחאב בן
קוליה ואל צדקיה בן מעשיה הניבאים לכם בשמי לשקר koh amar Hashem
Tzevaot Elokei Yisrael el Achav ben Kolaya v'el Tzidkiya ben Maaseiya haniba'im
lachem bishmi lasheker etc. etc. So now we have two people
that are called אחאב, Achav, but it's not the king of Israel,
and צדקיה, Tzidkiya, not the king of Judah. They are prophets and
they are false prophets. ולקח מהם קללה לכל גלות יהודה אשר בבבל
לאמור ישימך ה' כצדקיה וכאחאב אשר קלם מלך בבל באש. v'lukach mehem
klala l'chol galut Yehuda asher b'Vavel lemor yesimcha Hashem k'Tzidkiya u'ch'Achav asher
kalam melech Bavel ba'esh.
The פסוק pasuk continues to say there is like a curse from
them to all the diaspora, to all the exile of Judah in
בבל Bavel to say, think about it, ישימך השם, Yisimecha Hashem, right,
should be כאפרים וכמנשה keEphraim ucheMenashe who lived in a different גלות
galut and strengthened the Jewish people, right? They lived in גלות מצרים
galut Mitzrayim and strengthened the Jewish people. Here we have people that
lived in גלות בבל galut Bavel and weakened the Jewish people and
there and it says אשר קלם מלך בבל באש. asher kalam melech
bavel baesh. I just I didn't see it anywhere but I love
that קללה klalah קלם kalam connection. But קלם kalam means toast. It's
like and see the גמרא Gemara continues אשר שרפם לא נאמר אלא
אשר קלם. asher srafam lo neemar ela asher kalam. It doesn't say
that they were burned, they were they were roasted. Awful image, but
they had a process that's called קליה. kliyah. We do it like
to seeds or nuts. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי
מלמד שעשאן כקליות. amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai melamed
sheasaan kekliyot. We have a
teaching that they were like like toasted wheat, like toasted seeds on
the fire. Why? Why do we just like toast people? יען אשר
עשו נבלה בישראל וינאפו את נשי רעיהם. yaan asher asu nevalah beYisrael
vayinafu et neshei rei'ehem. They did a
bad
thing and and were adulterous with the wives of their neighbors or
the wives of their friends. What did they do? מאי עבוד? mai
avud? And now we know what they were trying to do to
the daughter of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar and therefore we know that that was
their practice to do that with the Jewish people. אזלו לגבי ברתא,
azlu legabei barta, sorry, דנבוכדנצר. deNevuchadnezzar.
They went to the daughter of נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnezzar. אחאב אמר לה כה
אמר השם השמיעי אל צדקיה. Achav amar lah koh amar Hashem hashmeyi
el Tzidkiyah. This is the word of השם. Hashem. You should be
intimate, you should be
sexual with צדקיה. Tzidkiyah. וצדקיה אמר כה אמר השם השמיעי אל אחאב.
veTzidkiyah amar koh
amar Hashem hashmeyi el Achav. Basically each one of them is trying
to seduce the daughter to be with the other guy. אזלה ואמרה
ליה לאבוה.
azlah veamrah
leih leavuh.
She went and said it to her father. אמר לה אלוהיהם של
אלו שונא זימה הוא כי אתו לגבך שדרינהו לגבי. amar lah eloheihem
shel elu soneh zimah hu ki atu legabach shadreinhu legabi. He says,
also beautiful, the גויים goyim know the תורה, Torah, is that right?
Thank you. I'm going to I'm going to wrap. He says their
God hates
abhors this kind of behavior. When they come to you, send them
to me. Right? So when they came to her, כי אתו לגבה
שדרתהו לגבי אבוה, ki atu legabah shadratehu legabei avuh, she sent them
to her father. He said to them, אמר להו מן אמר לכון?
amar lehu man amar lachon? Who
what God said to you what? Who said this to you? They
said הקדוש ברוך הוא. Hakadosh Baruch Hu. והא חנניה מישאל ועזריה שאלתינהו
ואמרו לי אסור. veha Chananyah Mishael veAzaryah shealtinhu veamru li assur. I
asked חנניה Chananya, מישאל Mishael, ועזריה v'Azarya, and they said this is
not allowed. Which is fascinating. That means נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar already thought of
having his daughter have sex with a Jewish prophet, right? He for
some reason he wanted to breed her maybe with a Jewish prophet.
חנניה Chananya, מישאל Mishael, ועזריה v'Azarya said אסור. assur. אמרו ליה אנן
נמי נביאי כותייהו לדידהו לא אמר להו לדידן אמר לן. amru leih
anan nami nevi'ei kevathaihu ledidhu lo amar lehu ledidan amar lan. We're
also prophets like them.
To them he didn't say, to us he said to us. אמר
להו, amar lehu, okay fine. אמר להו אנא בעינא דאיבדקינכו. amar lehu
ana beina deivadkinechu. I will check you just like sixty seconds, just
like I checked חנניה Chananya, מישאל Mishael, ועזריה, v'Azarya I will check
you too. אמרו ליה אינון תלתא הוו ואנן תרין.
amru leih inun tlata
havu veanan terein.
They were three, of course they survived, we're only two. אמר להו
בחרו לכון מאן דאיתו בהדייכו. amar lehu bacharu lachon man deito bahadayichu.
Choose yourself a third guy. אמרו יהושע כהן גדול. amru Yehoshua Kohen
Gadol. סברי טפי יהושע דנפיש זכותיה ומגן עלן. savri tfei Yehoshua denafish
zechuteih umagen alan. They thought יהושע Yehoshua has זכות zechut and he
will protect them. We will see it did not work. Sorry to
cut this short. Thank you for being with us. Have a fabulous
day. Regi,
help me stop it.
Yeah. Just some...
Yeah. Yeah it said low battery. Yeah it's low battery.